Do we?
So I'd like to call the public hearing to order. It is 07:00.
The purpose of the public hearing is to discuss application number 2302,
property of Robert Fiadamo Junior 43 Aspinall Road in Andover.
Application for a special permit to allow for the construction of a detached
accessory apartment in accordance with section 4.11
in section 23 of the Andover zoning regulations.
I don't recognize
the three of you. I got the you was the property owner last time. Yes, sir. That's my wife, Janine. His wife, Janine. Okay.
It's not in that contract. And very good.
And
and so
>> Okay. So it's the iPad that was muted. I'll let him come back in here. You can get down. Okay.
>> So anyhow,
I saw that we had, you know, posted online some new
information,
and,
if the contractor can give us an update of what
you, you provided to us since the last meeting, I'd appreciate that.
And then we'll we'll add the questions.
I I
don't think there is anybody in attendance here tonight outside of the commission that is
looking to comment on your application.
So
Okay. Given that, we'll we'll just proceed
>> with the with your presentation. Okay. Hello, everyone. My name is Nicholas Slulik. My company is Woodcraft Designs Inc. I'm a builder at Hayman, Connecticut here to represent
the BMI for
the application that I've been for you. What
I've updated since the last meeting was
the
central stewardship exemption
application,
the approval
that I received
from
that.
That came. Yeah.
And I improved
the prints. There was some confusion about dimensions,
and there were things that needed to be handled,
like the heating and cooling system,
with the finished ceiling height of the building.
And just in-depth dimensional and
the elevation,
so that it was just a little more clear
for everyone. The other thing we did also is we added the missing information
on the second hand. So we we killed
I have two paper copies. I know my PDF is too. Yeah. I
>> think good. I will, you know, try and get the the drawings up here so you can this changes a little bit easier.
Let's
let's start at the bottom and we'll work well second from the bottom the same plan revised.
Yes.
>> Okay. So the some of the information that was missing the last time was how we were gonna provide power,
how we were gonna safeguard the waste,
and how we were gonna supply water
to the building. So that's shown,
and it's identified.
We
also needed to show some parking, some additional parking. So we were building
four parking spaces
and
they wanted to
or you wanted to show exactly where the tank was
and how the system is laid out.
We didn't have any information
on the fields per day.
The file is not complete, so there's no hassle for the fields, but
the fields are beyond
the septic tank, as you can see on the print.
And I think that was
that was all.
Okay.
>> Here's a quick recap of that, and then we'll go to
the updated
drawings.
Yeah.
Yeah. I've got that.
>> Yes, so I think the only thing you added here with the the heat pump on the outside. Yeah, I showed that I showed the
>> finished ceiling height at eight feet
and I gave you the correct dimensions the exterior the outside dimension, which
is 12 by 29.
The little
mudrooms
on close numbering is six by six
that gives us the total
square footage of three seventy six.
And.
I believe that was all that was at. What
color do we plan to have the
>> You can right now, it's a it's it's kind of a baby. You can say it's a We're not baby. We're not altering anything.
>> Yeah. One of the few things we
we have to ensure is the compatibility
with the naval guidelines, you know, didn't want it to share truths through. But we don't need that. Yeah. Yep. Okay. Very good.
And then,
is is Steve had said the the approval from the sanatorian is in there, and,
I wasn't gonna bring that up unless somebody wanted to see that.
I have everything.
Is there anything else you wanted to present to the commission for with respect to
tonight?
>> On the application. I bet I'd be happy to fill in some questions if if anyone has any questions.
>> Okay. At at
this point, I guess, to the property owners, have anything that you'd like to add at this point?
>> No. I mean, we're just taking the existing. We're not showing off or, you know, we're blocking any move. They gotta hear you. So, we're doing this for our daughter. I mean, it's not rental property. I mean, she's only giving me money, but that's different. Yeah. Yeah.
>> But, you know, it's just, it's just something original. Okay.
Great.
Jim, I saw that you added the checklist,
online this afternoon.
In your mind, is the application complete, and does it meet our requirements there?
>> I believe it is yes.
The only thing that I didn't address, I didn't go back to this is lighting.
We did speak. I did speak briefly about it with the applicant on and
what we've done in the past is just had a condition that
any any lighting
being accordance with the with the zoning rinks.
Don't recall it being any lighting added to the plan. No, no.
>> But
on the front door,
and that's it. That's another set on my part. The front door gets a light every exterior.
Door has to have a light by code so
you know we'll probably have an overhead light in the mudroom will have a
wall light going into the the front door and possibly.
A floodlight as you come up the driveway,
a motion floodlight.
I need to discuss that with the owners left. We thought it was happening. So
just Because the part of the garage is not gonna be the door inside on the grass properties with the door. Okay. Yeah.
>> As you're coming up the driveway, you're gonna be looking at the leftover.
>> Sizes are three o by five six, so that means cigarettes. I had to run that. Somebody's saying that they're by the the billing inspector. Any questions with him? I know he doesn't get this till after all this is done, they get that far. So
none more cash.
>> Any other questions from the commissioner?
Okay. I have no other questions
too. So at this point, do any of the commission members
feel there is a need to hold the public hearing open
any longer?
Or are we ready to close the public hearing?
I don't know if it's a public hearing.
>> We ever determine whether
the weather needed to be conditioned space or what in terms of power of rent?
Our
our regs
don't really
address that.
You may have seen
if you had a chance to read the the graph
change, goes like, what what
what is an architectural plan? And that's when after we left the last meeting, I went out and and worked on that a little bit because that seemed to be the key to what what we had to specify that in our particular plan. And
all the definitions that I found were very vague.
And so I thought most of those issues would probably go back to meeting the the building official,
you know, to make sure that it's done to code.
So I did not
I looked at it that there was nothing in our regulations that required it to be conditioned.
If I were to build this thing, I probably wouldn't condition the mudroom either. I have one that's not conditioned right now.
And so I said,
that's okay with me. That's
how I came through that particular question.
And
it means to square footage.
It just
bear
With the with the mushroom. And again,
the the we're
we're kind of getting into the deliberation a little bit, but if we're we're trying to make
figure out whether or not we can close the hearing, the
two things came into play.
The
we have a square footage requirement
in our regulations today,
which he needs.
Our our regulation doesn't specify whether it's needs to be net square footage or gross square footage, and it might make a difference if we did, but we didn't specify that. We just said square footage.
And I think
I'm pretty confident that,
the
minimum square footage
requirement is no longer legal anyhow.
And so if this plan would have initially, I thought I was gonna have to go out and change the regulation before we get out of this hearing
because I wanna get rid of that. But they added the mudroom on there. They got it up to the current conditions
or regulations as they stand today.
And so we need that.
But
certainly, if we disapproved it
because of the size,
they would have, you know, they'd have the ability to go appeal it and
win that. And so I was happy
that the square footage met our requirement. I didn't have to hurry through and change the regulations before they got there. I think my group's a nice addition to it. I think that worked out well.
And and that's
how I came through this work footage. Yeah.
>> I usually plan came in before
before the application is two forty square feet because they're working with a 10 by 24 foot building,
pointing out the two fifty requirement. If you look at section 23, the definitions,
they give you a few hints on how to bump that up or cover for instance.
And they did this for two reasons. I think one is to meet regulations, but also they wanted to go to space to everyone to decide each other for one particular or a cat entry.
Any
>> other questions from any of the commission members?
Thanks, Kevin. Any other questions or comments from the commission?
Do any of the Commission members have any concerns about closing the public hearing at this time?
Hearing none, I'll close the public hearing. It's time 07:15.
And at 07:15,
we will open the regular meeting with Planning and Zoning Commission.
The
roll call and seating of alternates.
Leanne, are you with us?
Yes.
>> Okay. So I will I will seat you as a regular member. You can see the screen?
Yes
okay very good
>> well I discovered
just excuse me in the course of
getting ready for the meeting that there was a link shown
and this obviously is what I called in on so I was prepared to go out the door if I couldn't get through.
But I can hear you and I can see the material that's being put on the screen.
>> Good. So you're welcome to give us your feedback on on how it works from your end and
we'll go from there. So we have full regular commission
tonight.
Anne Gourmet,
Scott Persaud, Steve Nelson, Leanne Hutchinson,
and myself.
So none of the alternates,
although all three alternates are present,
none of them will be seated.
Additions and changes to the agenda, I,
I would like to propose two
changes to the agenda, and I'd like to add new item,
new business 5B,
a pre application conference for the senior community center.
And then under old business,
I would like to change
old business to fifth b,
which is an update on the senior community center. I wanted to get that up so
that we got it earlier in the program so people didn't have to stick around any longer than they wanted to with that,
to have a discussion on the draft
accessory dwelling unit changes.
And then we'll renumber
the current,
new business five b, the, boundary agreement
item,
that'll now be five c.
So I make a motion to,
approve those three changes.
Thank
you, Scott. Any discussion on that?
Hearing none, I'll call for a vote. Anne for May?
Scott. Steve.
Aye. Leanne.
Aye.
>> And I vote aye as well so that motion passes
five zero zero.
Any members of the public have any comments before we, we start the discussion
tonight on the verdadis?
Seeing none,
we'll go on to,
the first item of new business, application 23Dash02,
the application of Robert Yamato 43
Aspinall Drive,
seeking a special permit to allow detached accessories in accordance
with section four. 11 to the annual resuming regulations.
At this point,
our zoning agent said that that about the application was complete
and met the requirements.
We had a couple of items of discussion in the public hearing but any other
questions or comments
on the application at this point?
Hearing none,
I'll make a motion to approve
application 2302
for accessory
dwelling unit.
Second.
Any
other discussion on the motion?
Hearing none, I'll call for a vote. Ian for me.
Scott?
Aye.
Steve? Aye. Leanne?
>> And I vote aye as well?
The motion passes five zero zero.
You're all set. Thank you very much. We appreciate it, and the town's done to us so far.
Yeah. Thank you.
Thank you.
>> Next up is,
item five b, the senior community center
pre application conference. Okay,
>> folks. Most of you probably
know me, I would hope, by now.
I only made about 10 of these, so all of you will have to share my
I apologize
for not giving the mapping to the clinician earlier.
Got this from the surveyor today at about four.
And I had a quick set of notes. Also, the second sheet
is regarding the town to parking regulations.
So I think that's one of the things we're gonna kinda focus on.
Alrighty. So real quick.
We're,
the town will probably be a month or so away from
a full blown application
for the community center.
But there are a few questions that I would like to discuss with the commission because I wanna make sure we're on the same, you know, page regarding the application
prior to.
So let me just bring up the.
Okay, so the first item I want to talk about is parking
because that's been one of the things that's been pretty contentious.
This is an aerial shot that shows the fire department, the existing town hall in the Andover Elementary School.
So
there's a couple things right now currently designated
for fire department only there are 12 spots.
The town hall has 38 spots
and over elementary school
has
in the lower parking lot
and 38 in the upper parking lot.
So between those three entities there's 191
spaces.
I've been watching,
you know, during most daytime operations,
you know, we tend to be running,
you know, at most 50 cars collectively between the town and fire department in the school. So we're at less than a third of the normal capacity
for parking.
So today I took a snapshot at 10AM.
There were 39 cars parked in the AES parking lot, 12 total at Town Hall,
one car for Fire Department.
And and
so again 51 today,
which is about a 26%
utilization
rate.
So
your parking regulations
are section 12.
And there's going to be a couple things we need to to talk about. The first is
you the regulations
have a matrix
that
allows for minimum and maximum level of parking by type of usage.
Unfortunately,
lot of the types of usage we have don't really match up to what's in your regulations.
So what I attempted
to do is,
you know, pick the category that is closest
to what is required.
So I also wanted to talk a little bit about usage patterns.
The annual volunteer fire department has about 35 active members.
When you look at their parking utilization,
generally their heaviest parking utilization is Wednesday night for their their drills and their crane inspectors.
And there's been up to 20 cards here for Wednesday nights. Usually there's a few less than that,
but assume
roughly 20 cards
during the peak fire department time.
The town hall or ordinary conditions are typically up to eight employees working here at any given time,
and one to five members of the public.
So our load on this building,
you know, tends to be 15 vehicles or less.
There's also senior transportation
vehicle store
and we have three vehicles for senior transportation.
And
at any given time there may be a driver that just showed up and parked her own. You can say on average right now you can anticipate up to four vehicles
parking here for senior transportation.
So
if you look at
what we're going to want to do is consider this overall
as a shared parking situation,
because the reality is the town hall and the bar department shared parking
and the town hall and the school shared parking.
And when there's big events at one versus the other, we all use our cross parking.
So we are effectively
now
we have shared parking, so we're not planning on.
You know, changing that.
So when we look at the regulations
and how they specify
each
each use.
There's no real use in your in the regs for establishing
parking for fire department.
So I assumed one spot for every two members.
Okay,
which would be 17 total spark parking spots for the fire department.
In the town hall, the closest category in the list would be as far as I could tell would be a professional office building,
which is two to five spaces per 1,000 square feet,
nets out somewhere between thirteen and thirty one vehicles for the town hall.
The community center.
Again, the closest thing I could find in there would be an indoor recreational
facility,
which is two to 10 per 1,000 square feet.
So, the size of the community center that requires between five and twenty five spaces.
There's no category for public schools, but there is for private schools.
And if you look in that is based on the max capacity
for the building
in terms of students.
So if you look at the max capacity
that says the school should have somewhere between fifty four and one hundred and seven parking spots.
So currently they have 141.
So the school has quite a bit in excess of what your regulations allow for maximum parking. In other words, if they were building that today,
you would have required them to put in a much smaller law. And that kind of makes sense because
I've looked a few times.
And on average, there's less than 40 cars in that lot out of 141.
So it's definitely underutilized.
So where are we in terms of total parking?
If you look at the combined uses in your regulations
for the fire department, the town hall, the community center and the school,
you come up with a minimum if you take the minimum for each of those categories of 69 spots
and a maximum of 180.
And since you have 191
available,
I think to me there's a pretty good evidence that there's sufficient parking and that that should be
a non issue.
And the second question that was raised is can Town Hall
qualify
for parking
without you know you said the school was something completely separate.
So the answer is, if you take the requirements for the fire department and the town hall in the school
and you accept the minimum levels.
The minimum
required
for those three occupations
would be 35
spots
and between the town hall and the fire department, there are
either 50 or 51 depending on how you. So, regardless of whether you include the school parking or not,
we should still qualify minimum parking levels.
If we include the school, we're actually over the maximum parking. So
my suggestion would be that the Commission allow the application to go through without any additional parking,
because we've got plenty of parking
combined between the three.
So that's the first
one is parking.
And then what I'd like to do is take you all through
the
then.
So obviously you can see that. Leanne, I assume you cannot see that, correct?
I don't think so.
>> Hey,
Eric. If you just click on the screen and say share, it'll show share if you click on the screen, or you click on the individual and say share.
>> So go to the share itself?
The screen itself? That screen you're on before.
The Zoom screen.
>> These buttons down the bottom for the share.
Alright.
The blue.
>> Right, but the problem is that the oh, that is the one that I wanted to share. Okay, I'll shut up now. Thank you.
So
am I looking at the right one? No, but we'll start with this one. Okay. So this one is not the full survey,
which is what I want to start with.
So let's see if I
You know what? Script. Let's talk about that one. This one is
the details
of
the basic plan
for the community center.
So to orient you right now,
we are sitting
right here in the Andover Town Hall in the community room.
So the proposed building location is directly behind
this building and turned in about a 45 degree angle.
And the angle of the building is determined by essentially optimizing it for Solar South.
So the main access of the building
faces Solar South.
So what you see is the intention to use the main entrance as the town hall as the entrance also to the community center,
a turning circle
that is large enough
to take emergency vehicles.
You can see the driveway
right here
that goes to the existing
Andover Elementary School garage,
And this also feeds to a
semi established
dirt
or gravel path
that is the access way to the lower playgrounds for the school
and also at location to at least one of the oil tanks for the school.
So that will be maintained
during construction.
Okay, if you look up here
where I'm indicating right here, that is the current leach field.
This is a combined leach field for the town hall
and for
the fire department. Currently,
the Community Center will be added to this building.
If you can see there's this is a this trench
goes both directions.
And then there's a second trench line here with the second distribution
box.
So the intention is to just
fit out the fourth leg of this.
So the the septic,
the additional capacity capacity for for the the septic system will go there. And then directly behind that is enough room for reserve system.
If it turns out, you know, some point future, we have an issue with the existing system that gives you a reserve or repair area system.
So about two weeks ago,
the
the engineer along with Eastern Highlands Health District
and the town crew
dug an EPIC test there.
The modeling level
was more than four feet deep,
and they went down seven feet without hitting lynch and no sign of active water. So that was very positive.
And the
was also two perk tests. Then I take it back one perk test compete completed.
And it matched exactly the values that they got in 1990,
which is saying the soil conditions haven't really changed.
So the system should be approved as designed.
Talking to sanitary and he was pretty convinced that there wasn't going be any problems with that.
We do show on the map a future pickleball court.
That was a request from several individuals
that pickleball
is going to be a thing and you better anticipate being able to book the courts back there. So this is a location
of
what could go in the future. Just saying that there's technically room there to put into courts without interfering
with the septic system. We're not intending to put them in right now.
The reason they're shown as separate and not combined courts is because of the grade there.
The
one court will be have to be about three and a half feet lower than the other court. So each one of them will need its own individual fencing,
a little more expensive way to build it.
But it's a lot cheaper than bringing in a lot of gravel.
The community garden
will be located between the shed here and the edge of the pickleball court,
right about where I'm indicating right there.
That way they can use rainwater off of both sheds.
And it's still approximate to the parking area. So it's easy to get at.
That will public works will bring in additional bill,
but
it won't interfere with the existing system because
you know we're not getting close enough to to the actual leach field that we need to worry about bringing septic sand or anything like that.
So before
>> I go any further, does anybody here have any questions about
this portion and or the parking?
>> Are there going be any changes
based on handicap parking requirements?
>> So.
There's going to be a few things
if you notice
right here.
There's two additional spots for handicapped parking that will be installed right in there.
And then we also had one request for somebody who has
is
is not
in wheelchair,
but only has the ability to walk very short distances.
So we did put in one additional van accessible handicap spot,
you know, basically as close to the door as it was humanly possible.
So there'll be one super close parking,
handicap spot, and then two more additional ones just for the community center, which is what's what's code required.
What's not on this map, which will be added is your regulations do require us to
make accommodations
for
bicycle parking, which is a wonderful thing in the Community Center anyway.
So we have to figure out how many spots we need. We do have four at the front of the town hall, But I would anticipate
as part of this and we have
more spots at the school, but I would anticipate we'll put additional
bicycle parking
somewhere
right by the front door to the community center
to meet section 12.7
of your regs.
The one, one of the things I wanted to ask the commission
is
for relief
for the section in your regulations
that requires
a
for
you don't have community uses directly listed out in your regulations.
But
most
industrial business and things of that nature require dedicated loading spot.
And I would ask whether the Commission would consider waiving that for this application.
So in the reason is the the main floor only has one main door.
There is a side door here, but it's not really great for loading.
So most things that come in here that require loading would come around the circle park right there, and then have direct sidewalk access into the front.
So
what I would propose is that US Commission
allow us to get away with not having a dedicated loading spot.
Because if we
we have sufficient parking that we could do it, you know, it's not an issue, but there's no clean place on this map to designate a spot for parking without taking up one of the two handicapped parking spots down there, which I would very much like not to do.
So when we come to the application, I don't know whether
it and I don't expect her.
You know, a definitive answer tonight.
But does anybody on the commission? Would anybody be opposed to us submitting a waiver
for the requirement
for a loading space?
>> Would there be some semi net
temporary stopping there for loading and unloading kind of thing?
Because that's a spot where you would not tend to have it, like, parked.
It's temporary type of thing. Yeah. I mean,
>> you know,
The
that that's obviously going to be where the you know, like when senior transportation drops off the seniors,
they'll park right along that sidewalk so they can have direct access down to the sidewalk.
But that's not going to be straight for parking in any way, shape or form. In fact, we probably want to, I mean, we really don't want anybody parking there for any kind of duration because that will be the fire lane access to that facility also.
Yeah. That
that makes total sense. Yeah.
Yep. That's perfect. Yeah.
>> There's a car
south there, bus.
Lori, I'm gonna
be able to get through in that circle. Is there enough room? I can't tell. A car. Yes.
>> Yeah, it's not a width issue.
It's a
long vehicle
requires a much greater turning radius there than,
you know, even even a large bus school bus certainly wouldn't get through there if somebody was parked there.
We would need to put that road in the loading past the center point so that as somebody comes around, they have an upgrade to reset. Right. If it's too early in the circle, nobody get one. That's what we see in pushing past.
Concur.
Other questions regarding that?
Does anybody in the commission have any general questions
on the application?
What they're seeing? What their concerns are?
>> In the setbacks for requirements,
they're all met by the location of the building on there.
>> Yeah, the
the reality is the town owns all the properties.
So I mean, that was a question I asked Mark branch directly,
and he essentially said that
the
you know, as a town, you can set those property boundaries anywhere you want, because technically it is all all towns property.
So
yeah, there's nothing
there's
the closest anything comes to that would be a true property line would be the the easement for the gas line and nothing we're doing is other than the
other than the pickleball court and that's far enough away that I don't think that's an issue either.
So no, there should not be any issues
with
side yard setbacks.
The one that
the town would consider and again, it depends
on how the commission
feels.
This piece of property
right here there is
I'm going show you the other screen.
There's
an existing bead line that's right here.
This parcel that the town hall was on was originally cut out at
exactly
one acre. Well, not even one acre was cut out in exactly
40,000
square feet because that was the minimum allowed
under zoning regs in the back area,
which was deeded to the town at the same time
was technically a separate parcel.
So
the
question that we struggled with is does that back parcel.
It does not touch any town road.
Therefore, is it,
you know, is it a legal parcel?
So I mean we can get rid of that deep line. We just file a new deep description with these two parcels merge.
If that's a concern by the Commission.
Again, you know Mark Grant said you can essentially ignore it
because it's all pound property and you can set the line any way you want,
but I recognize that
depending on how you read the regs, that may not be the interpretation you get to, and we would be happy to file this with a new deep line
that shows that removed in the two parts partial moved.
Now the other thing we have been considering
and this isn't something
that has a.
You know, a final
decision is,
you know, presumably will still will end up being the talking point between the town and the school
is
one of the concerns was
was
to make it cleaner
to clean separate
what is town property and under town authority and what is school property and under school authority.
So one of the things we are talking about doing
is essentially
drawing
the boundary line,
moving it over by dropping a single pin.
This would move about point one acres of land and transfer it between the school and the town,
essentially, but that would give
that would basically put the entire proposed driveway
in the town portion
and leave everything else in the school so it it does not affect any of the school parking.
It doesn't affect any of that doesn't affect any your egress.
You know, it's we're talking about somewhere
just under 4,000
square feet of land. So we're talking about a pretty small piece.
That's not final. That's,
but that is one, you know, one option.
You know, I think we can clearly do this
and apply
without it. But I do think that makes things
cleaner
and makes it easier to understand who's responsible for what.
We had also talked for a while about officially merging
the school
and
fire
department properties.
Initially,
the surveyor had some concerns
because the septic system
for the
fire department
was not on the prop parcel
attached
to that. So we asked that question to the zoning attorney also.
And he said it doesn't really matter as far as the law.
You know, if by
virtue of the fact that this parcel
has contains the septic fields
for this building,
this building, the proposed building and the school is de facto emerged partial anyway.
So he said we can safely
ignore that.
You know, so given that there's no reason to to kind of merge these two parcels might might as well just keeping
keep it simple so we don't have to write any more deep descriptions than we have to.
Although there are on the same particle there are separate zones, and you could stop there. Right? There are two septic systems
on the property. There is a large system
that is located
right here. That is the school system.
And
there's an additional
portion to that.
And that is right here.
At one point, the last
two sets of trenches
had filled in and stopped functioning.
So they built an additional capacity
off to the side here.
But the last time that got dug up when we looked in the in the distribution boxes,
there was no evidence that any affluent had ever flown in with it. So this portion of the system for the school as does not appear to have ever been been used, even though it's physically there and around.
The town's
combined system
is
right here.
And this is fed already
from two different spots.
The town
has a septic tank right here
that feeds into the first distribution box here, and then gets split to the second distribution box.
And the fire department system actually enters the field
on this end of the first trench,
because their capacity.
So they were allowed at the time to just instead of trenching all the way over and putting everything in in the central distribution
box.
So this part's not going to change this part's not going to change.
What will change is there will be an additional septic tank
for
the
town hall for correction, the community center,
and that will go into the central D box.
And then this leg,
the fourth leg will be completed,
And that should be the septic system
for this.
Because the septic system will now cover three separate buildings
with
three different uses.
This does require not just these Eastern Highlands Health District approval,
but it does require
state approval also,
which I talked to our Senator in fact, he thought that was not an issue
that
he didn't have any concerns with that and thought the state would not also.
But just so that you know that that will take both those approvals
before we're allowed to build it.
>> Which the little lead line that said, you know, the dotted thing that goes through the boardroom school there. Alright, so
>> this gets back to when
Endover Elementary School was first built here
in the late 40s.
This was the original boundary
right here
of the school property
that land was deeded to the town from
a previous first selectman, a guy named Percy Cook,
who if you walk back there you might notice the trails
named after him. So he initially needed this in
like '46.
The school was built in 1947.
And then the town needed the land back to Percy Cook. And then Percy Cook, then deeded the town a bigger outline
and deeded them more land so this outer boundary right there
was the second
version
of him giving land to the town, And it increased this from, you know, like 5.8
acres to, to somewhere around 10 acres.
And that all occurred at, you know, basically in one shot.
It was a little weird because you see all the stuff in the town,
basically,
quick claiming it back to Percy.
And then Percy
quick claim the different
deep description back to the town all at one time. So it took a while to
get that. But does that answer your question?
Okay. And this is what I would have preferred to have shown first, but
couldn't find it. So this is the overall boundary survey,
which goes all the parcels.
This is the fire complex right here.
This is the town hall complex
right here.
And this is all of
the Andover Elementary School. And this again shows that initial
survey boundary
by person put, you can pretty much ignore this one.
This is just on there because it's
a bunch of things in the past referred to it. So we have surveyor showed that
on the map.
So
the
reason I wanted to talk to you guys a little bit about this
is this is something that will
prior to us filing this
will require
us to do an 08/24
application
with the zoning commission.
And the reason why is that
if you look at the boundary between the school
and
the Hawes
property,
are surveyor thinks the last surveyor that did this got the boundary wrong.
Not a lot in this area right here.
It's off somewhere around five feet.
And then there's this has been drawn
this little triangle there or
square.
You know, it was also identified as there's a difference between
the written feed and the actual survey data from the last surveyor.
So what would have to happen
is the surveyor basically said there's enough
difference between those points,
they can't
do something to a two level of accuracy,
because there's there's too many conflicting,
you know, prior survey and boundary,
you know,
boundaries there.
So their suggestion is that we do a boundary line agreement with the Hawes family.
In this area right there,
we're talking,
you know,
a pretty small amount, you know, 200 feet times about five feet wide.
So, you know, something about 1,000 square feet of difference between there. And then this little triangle right there,
which is, you know,
give or take 4,000
square feet. So there's somewhere about 5,000 square feet.
You know, 1.3
acres
difference between the two surveys.
So,
so but it's not anything that affects school or school operations.
So in the interest of having a clean survey,
I would recommend that we
you know, at some point, we'll officially do an 08/24
application.
You know, and if you guys approve it, then we would go ahead and file this.
I did tell the superintendent that this was coming, but I didn't have the mapping. I will share the mapping with them.
And you know, Gary, if you guys have any feedback on that, you know, feel free. But I don't believe this in any way affects your operations.
And obviously, we had to get the Hawes family to agree to that also.
But it just makes it you know, once the boundary line agreement is in place,
then forevermore,
you know, it's pending, you know where it is.
So that's,
that's where we are regarding the survey.
Is it currently pending?
Far as I know, it is not.
>> You're done with the question. I didn't hear that. Is that is it currently pending?
>> No. I don't don't think so. At least the mapping doesn't show it.
So it's going to open in there.
>> Yeah,
rebar
fence
line there.
So in when you look at the old maps, old mapping,
sometimes has this drawn here, and sometimes has drawn there.
You know, I don't think there's any,
you know, that that's one of the unfortunate things surveyors have to do is wait through all the old stuff and try to figure out what the original intention was.
And,
you know,
in the original mapping for this was pretty crude that the same was done.
Other questions at this point,
or comments or concerns by the commission?
Anybody in the audience have questions or comments or concerns?
>> The neighbors
have their lot surveyed?
Did the people that are next to fill that boundary question and they had their property surveyed that ever match up?
>> There is a survey for the Hawes property.
And that does not match completely the anchor engineering survey.
I think this survey matches closer to what the survey
and the deep description for that property was.
There is apparently an existing easement to drain
from the school property on to the Hawes property,
But that will not be affected or changed by this
application.
I don't think they're going to complain they're going to get a few 1,000 square feet more land, they're not going to get anything that's practical usable, but but it should not negatively affect them in any way.
So I don't see any reason why they would.
I have not talked to both of them. Have not shown the mapping yet. But I have had a verbal discussion with Kim Hawes, and said that, you know, the town will be coming even some point to do this.
So
questions.
>> I think so
the drawing shows the gazebo
is on the school property. Has there been any feedback
from the school on
whether they would like to
get rid of that or they're happy with that one way or the other? I think that was a little bit of a surprise.
>> It actually wasn't that much of a surprise because if if you looked at the old GIS data,
that's kind of what it showed all along. I know everybody I talked to told me they were sure that the line went straight down the gazebo, half on school property and half on town property.
You know, but when we actually surveyed, that's clearly not the case. I mean, obviously, the town has been maintaining a placebo
and the electrical
outlets and power for the gazebo comes from the town hall, not the school.
As long as the school doesn't have any
objection to that,
you know, that can
that can stay.
You know, I know the school board was offered a
possibility
of adjusting the lot line, which would have put that under town control, not school control. And I think the school board wasn't overly excited about that proposal.
Okay, so that's not incorporated in this.
Other questions?
Alright, a little luck. We'll see a full blown application
next month.
I will be doing that presentation. That'll be the engineers from BSC.
Thank you, Eric. No problem.
>> Did the people
that are, here from the public get the opportunity to sign a little sign in sheet so we know for our minutes
who's here would be very good. Thank you.
That
concludes
item five bravo.
The
next item up is
just for
a very preliminary
run through discussion
regarding a different boundary agreement and possible eight twenty four referral for
purchase of the property owned by Stephen King on Burnett Brook Road.
It's probably better. Was gonna bring up the GIS map, which we know we're wrong. But
>> Let me see if I could share this.
And
so what you're looking at right here
is
the
the town owns a large piece of property which the transfer station is on
the town has access
to it up at several locations.
But one of the sides of that property
abuts a property owned by mister King,
and that's another one of those cases where there seems to be kind of pretty complete disagreement
as to between the deeds and the the
mapping that would file
as to where the boundary lines are.
So that's another case for the town.
At some point, it's going to have to do a lot line agreement with the homeowner on where the boundaries are.
So I'm going to show you a portion of the property to orient you this line in the way in 20 my my cursor down that is Burnett Brook.
This road right here is Burnett Brook.
So
in this part of the survey up to here, there's pretty good agreement about where the boundary
based on of the deed descriptions and there are new survey newer surveys for subdivision
in this area.
So this
point right there is fairly well established.
And then if you look at the other end of this survey,
Which is right here.
So to orient you, this is the Hop River Rail Trail.
And
right here where the road is, is where that little gravel parking area is
at Burnett Park.
Now that parking area is partially on DEEP
property.
And it is partially privately owned
by the owner that has this whole parcel.
So what the
town would like to do is the town would like to acquire
that section of Burnett Brook,
the frontage
to that along the road.
And the reason is that that probably one of the prettiest spots in town
along the Hop River Rail Trail. It's that big rapid section. It's also encompasses
the stone bridge
where the rail trail goes under.
And there's also a walking path that leads down the water.
And it's something that you know people are commonly using even though it's not private property.
So
what I
had told the homeowner in
to go back many years, I negotiated
a couple of times with the previous owner of this property
to see whether he would either sell or grant the town easement do that. Because I think this is
this is nice enough
that and that's really kind of one of the landmarks along the trail of the town should really own them.
Now the homeowner is amenable to giving back to the town as part of a boundary line,
you know, agreement,
in part because he doesn't want the liability to it, because there's an awful lot of, you know,
members of the public dropping over what's currently his property.
But he doesn't really want to put up signs or restrict it either.
So by putting that under town control,
you know, essentially alleviates
any
liability
portion from him. So he's happy to do that. And then the question is where this boundary goes.
I spent a couple hours this afternoon looking through all the mapping.
And he's right, I certainly can't figure it out.
So their surveyor,
Rob Hellstrom
made a
so this
this portion here is bounded by the road. So that one's fairly obvious.
This portion here, there's good survey data from
the old railroad.
So this is well established.
And based on the deep descriptions
this distance matches what's in the deep description
this distance matches what's in the deep description,
and so does this distance.
But what doesn't match is the angles they report don't really match.
You know, so this angle is probably off.
And it doesn't match between
the respective feeds and
previous
surveys,
none of which were really a two surveys, they were all, you know, pretty low resolution surveys.
So at some point,
there's going to need to be a boundary line agreement between the town
and the owner of this property to establish where that is because it looks like right now there's not enough.
There's not enough good data to definitively say where they intended to put that.
So this will also require an eight twenty four as well
the
acquisition of this property.
So when our surveyor reviews this and get back to us, it will probably go to the zoning attorney for review.
And then at some point, will come back to you as a commission for the coming for
You know, referral.
Now,
you might ask why do we care?
The Burnout Brook is one of one of only a couple of cold water streams in the town of Andover.
And because of that, there's a 200 foot upland review area
along the stream instead of just 100 feet like for a normal
for a lot of other things.
So the reality is the land that's in question that we're debating about
is it all in the upper review area, it's probably not billable anyway.
So regardless of whether we own it or the town owns it, it's probably not going to have to deal with any development pressure.
So essentially, all we're trying to do is get the boundary
about where it should be.
>> Questions on that?
I don't think I
don't know exactly how the property owner got started
on trying to figure out where the property was the first time he brought it in,
at least
to the best of his ability, understanding where the property
line went was right through the pasture that he had behind his house fenced in area. So he had
fenced in spot that's,
you know, pointed out to just as you get to the bend there and the property line went right through that little fenced in area and he was trying to
sort out.
What's
really there. And and he came, you know, forward to them in a very positive
manner. He's done a lot of work trying to sort out where the property line really is.
But he certainly had his fenced in pasture on the wrong side of the line for many, many years now, and and he's trying to make it right. And and so I
think
it's one of these cases where there could be a win win answer for both the property and where it would come.
>> Yeah. And if you read through the actual documentation
of this,
even if this went straight here, that would not match the descriptions
anyway.
So
the descriptions
don't match anything existing on the ground right now. So
it's I think the only practical way to sort this out is to come up with some kind of agreement between the two of us. And whether that agreement is a straight line that goes from here,
or whether
you know that it comes to some point here.
You know, that's
that I don't think anybody's we're not at the point where we're we're there yet.
I mean,
he would prefer not to go straight because that cuts off part of his pasture.
You know,
out of the Stockgate area.
>> And I looked at the GIS
line drawing today, and
it's
shows the property line a lot closer to the road than than any of these discussions do. They get the property lines
almost entirely on the roadside
of the river
and so.
That's probably not accurate either. That didn't match anything so right.
The important thing is that we, you know, come to an agreement on where the property line should be and then make it so. And
Eric's trying to figure out the most cost effective way of
right going out and doing is that northern and south line here.
Is that on any need? This line area
down on a deed anywhere?
>> No, actually, if you read the deed description
from this corner,
or from wherever this establishes,
you know,
they don't match one of them actually has it going
northwest
feet to some point there and going,
which would put basically this entire parcel
on town property.
But it also has this parcel,
this property extending way over on the other side of the road
and them owning a whole batch of land back here, which isn't correct either.
So
I mean,
hard to tell what the original.
>> So the reason that American South line is on this is what what reason is that there? Mean, this line right here. Yeah.
>> So
when they this boundary runs straight in this direction,
and there's a random iron in there.
So they picked that and said, Okay,
if we ran it straight there,
that would avoid it going through there.
Is that correct?
Maybe not.
I mean,
I'm not sure we're ever going to piece together
what the original intention
and where the quote unquote true boundaries are.
You know, I mean, like, if you think back to
the
parcel
that got sold,
that the town granted the easement to
Upper Riverside.
When they went in actually surveyed that property after they bought it, I mean, that property went from 76
acres down to 52 after
they actually surveyed it.
You know, when they pursued and finally got a boundary line agreement.
So, you know, we're only talking an acre, not a few acres. So it's not a huge disagreement.
But but I don't know that we'll ever get an exact
>> That North South Line is established by those residences to live with.
>> Question.
All those are residences. Right? This is the town line.
>> These are various different. These are lots.
This was a subdivision from around 1990.
And these properties extended all the way back to Wales Road.
So yeah, I think these are this probably accurate enough,
modern enough survey mapping to say this portion is correct.
You know, in this line is correct.
It's just the question where this boundary intercepts
that line
that is not really set in stone at this point.
At this point, that's that's the recommendation of the property owner, isn't it? That's where he would, you know, he's recommending he set the boundary there.
Right.
Yeah.
Yep. And the town could very easily,
you know, say, okay, we don't think that's correct. Well, you know, we think that's correct. But I mean, remember to we're getting,
you know, even if we are giving up a few acres of its land,
what we're getting out of it is the most scenic section
of Burnett Brook, and we're getting that under town control.
So from my perspective,
there's a lot to be gained by that.
You know, and we're not giving up anything that's buildable.
Because I mean, as many of you know, this, this, that interior portion of this property was one of the ones that that has always historically been under consideration
for higher density housing,
or you know, housing in some form or another.
But again, I don't think this would limit that because nothing we're talking about is
outside the 200 foot,
you know, upland review area.
>> So the way I check tonight, we just wanted to show you what's coming down the plate and
they're out there trying to make the property line better.
Yep. Whenever we start looking at property lines, it's always
the can of worms.
Into the town benefits by having a well liked property line out there if you ever do anything on that.
>> Yeah,
and we have to accept the fact that the town property is not surveyed either.
So there is some ambiguity of what the town actually owns there.
And the good news from my perspective is
the northern most edge of that property
is well defined by the the old railroad.
So that's easy.
The
part to the east
because there's all been subsequent development.
The town boundary along that whole side along Johnny Mills well established by the individual subdivisions lots that are cut out.
So this is the last portion of that that's really not defined.
So even if we don't survey the property ourselves,
we will with the with the boundary line agreement on that portion, we will have basically,
you know, enclosed all four sides of that property. So we should know pretty accurately where everything is.
>> Okay. That completes new business. Well,
okay.
One more. I
didn't renumber it, but, it now is
five delta,
discussion on monumentation and subdivision monuments.
And we had a discussion at the last meeting about some
some pins and monuments that were missing over in the Pine Ridge Drive
subdivision.
And
so I went back and and we looked at it's in the subdivision regs, which this was a subdivision, but it would apply to
any site plan
because
our regulations
provide that latitude.
But it talks about, you know, iron pins shall be installed in all live corners. The Commission shall require the installation of such monuments,
iron pins
is a condition of approval of the subdivision or resubdivision.
The building permit shall not be issued until required by invitation to corner pins are in place.
So,
you know, I talked to to Jim about that a little bit. We we should have had those bins in
place out there before they got a building permit.
I
don't
know that there's been, you know, as, as much as I would like coordination
between the the building official and the
zoning enforcement officer, but we're gonna try and
improve that a little bit so that that we can,
you know, get that kind of stuff taken care of and get that put in part of the process.
Now the other thing that that I discovered,
you know, reading through here is
in in,
I'll let Jim tell me where I run amok here, but it it talks about, you know, on section 21 dash four under enforcement for the building permits,
No building permit shall be issued for any activity which is not in conformance with provision of these regulations.
So how does the building official know whether or not he's in conformance with our regulations here?
It says no such permit shall be issued until the zoning enforcement officer is issued a certificate of zoning compliance
indicating that the plan submitted to the building official conform to these regulations.
So that's I think how the process goes.
Jim, correct me if I'm wrong. No, you're right. It's function of the zoning.
So the that
process
hasn't been
going on. I don't know if every building permit takes a certificate of zoning compliance or not.
Certainly what I'm looking for, you know, help on in this case is
for those those cases where a
nutrient allocation worksheet would be required around Andover Lake or something like that,
you know, that
the building official shouldn't be
issuing a building permit until he checks with Jim and Jim can say, oh, that takes a nutrient allocation worksheet and provides that backup or any other conditions of approval that we might put into
our
approval there that that provides that link. So that's something we've
got to work on to strengthen up a little bit there. But but our process, as it's written in the book,
seems to work pretty well.
We just haven't been as maybe
good as we should have been on a follow-up.
>> Historically, a
lot of kids were installed
after
prior to
at the time that the accident was done.
But
as you pointed out to me, that way the regulations way
the regulations read, and I will
make sure that that's compliance.
So in the past,
>> the zoning agent has all often weaved
and allowed them to pin it after
as a condition of getting a CO,
not as a condition of issuing the building permit.
And the reason is on a small loft, you're doing site work. It's very easy to run over and wreck the pins,
you know, and then nobody ever goes in and puts them back. So it's better to force
the surveyor to come back out after,
you know, do as folks who's building correctly pin the lock, and then give you a map and a set of ad books. That's what's done.
>> Doesn't have to be done. Well, makes sense. I got no background in any of this stuff. So all I do is read her her regs and check what I found by doing it.
We'll we'll try and get the ends in it better unless there's a good reason not to,
you know, come back and
do that. And and I still
there's still a fair amount of frustration that we we put out a plan,
and then we don't actually follow the plan all that well. And and that's something that I'll continue to try and get better. So
that's
that's all I want to say on my invitation unless anybody else had any
questions on that one.
Okay, we're gonna move on to old business, and first up is
an update on the gravel pit.
Jim, you got that? Sure.
>> I believe
that the gravel paid a slate for
hanging seating this week
and
planting on the
South Side.
We're we're along the Hutchinson property,
which is a concern of banks,
very tripping with respect to the turtles. Also, some of the silt fence is coming down to allow
turtles
to move more freely.
I did go out there with
weatherization and tank
with some concerns about the ability of that site to hold hold seat given the
the vastness of it, the
wind and perhaps
water migration.
And I hope to meet with
the owner this week, sent him a letter
and call him up.
Hopefully, we'll be meeting this week and going over detail.
It's also an issue that was raised.
Catherine Hutchinson has
probably all recall, has repeatedly
expressed concern about water
going into her property.
So the final plan I say the final plan, the Asheville, KA.
It's not particularly legible on on the
on the website.
And
some reason, you can't blow it up. Yeah. Whatever.
So there is a small portion of the property that does
drain
towards the what I call the hollow, which is the road along between
the properties, and that that road is is
in order to to regrade there, that would be filling in floodplain.
So something that's not gonna happen.
I'm gonna have to revisit that whole
issue because it will
come back the matter will come back to the commission
after May meeting, and I'd like to have that
resolved and resolved being understand why
why the owner did not grade it
all towards the back.
We would have to take another look at the plan and have another conversation with him.
That's all I really have. Was there any top soil on that side?
It's
lacking in the back. That's been pointed out to lacking towards the
towards the the
towards the
hill that was carved out.
That's
pointed out to him. Gonna be able it has to be able to take seed. The rest of the top soil that's that was on-site was was spread on the on the front portion.
And, actually, if you walk the site, make sure you have you can you literally can feel the the difference. You
don't even have to to look at it. It's
it's a sand on the back.
So we'll see how that he's he's aware that we'll have to see have to have to support and see
if it does or not.
>> So one of the things
that I felt
I didn't do very well in this particular case
is that
we repeatedly
and I guess Jim shared something you'll be here with me, but we repeatedly asked for a restoration plan
And we kept
not getting anything in writing
from the property owner
or the engineer.
And so Jim had sent several letters that way nothing comes back
and so.
Pinning down the property owner is what he actually agreed to has been very difficult.
And so
we need to do better on that going forward to make sure that we actually get a written plan so that we can go back to it and say that you didn't do this. Because as we already said,
even if we have a written plan,
the chances of the the first two of them weren't actually following it,
we don't always hit
hit what we should do. So
those those are a couple of things. I don't like being in a position where we put out a good plan and then we ignore it and nobody follows it and all that kind of stuff. That
frustrates all of us a little bit on that.
>> If you go back and review the recordings for the meetings, if you were presented
>> as a restoration plan? Well, I I just, you know, got the
we probably could.
It's
not really easy to do. Takes takes a lot of time. And
we're all limited on the amount of time.
I thought we were gonna get and and we're not far off, but, you know, I thought we were gonna come out with a good conclusion
at the end. It was probably still well.
But the the lesson learned is when we tell somebody to submit us a plan,
it's gotta be a the plan has gotta be in writing, so you go back and look at it.
So that's that's we'll
do better. You know? That's that's a process issue
in one of the things that we as a commission need to do when we have
when we approve something, and I thought hard about this with the accessory dwelling today tonight,
what conditions of approval can we go?
We're always in a hurry to get done with the thing. It what we need to do is develop the discipline that when before we leave a topic, we say, okay, here are all the conditions of approval. Make sure that they're in the minutes so we could go back to the minutes. So that's our okay.
What we should have done last meeting on the
accessory apartment
was we had a bunch of actions. They were all over the counter. We should have taken ten minutes at the end of that and said, okay. Let's go get the actions out here. Now my notes from the last agenda where I've written them write them down, I think they they did, in fact, cover everything that you were looking for,
but
we we need to work so that the minutes are are
bread and butter as far as what we expect other people to do. And then we just get the minutes out notice if you do this.
Yes or no? Yeah. That
saves us all a lot of working longer.
So
that's
what I'm gonna mean, and I am always in a new trying to get done on dying, all that stuff.
We gotta take a little bit more to make life easier later on.
I
did wanna spend just a couple of minutes on the Grad Accessory Rolling Unit changes. Eric, do you think you could
go to our website? And
Jim, did you get those posted under
the
They should be right with the application.
I'm here somewhere.
I
>> would have thought I think it was the second or third.
>> Apartments. This guy? Yes.
Okay. There we go.
I didn't actually see it. I
>> I was kind enough to post it. Leanne, are you able to see that?
What is this that you're trying to show now? Okay. I'm trying to show the draft change to the accessory
unit accessory
apartment regulations.
I
>> had a question on the, gravel pit before you moved on.
>> Okay have you got the accessory apartment you're seeing it now?
>> Yes I am. Can I still ask a question about the gravel pit? Oh go ahead yeah.
Yes. Based on what you said tonight, and, you know, we all know this has been going on for a very long time,
can we have something in place,
you
know, this does seem to be stagnating, can we have something in place
from the land use attorney if nothing has changed by our meeting next month?
And also, it doesn't seem reasonable to think that any grass would have grown in the timeframe that they
planted it over what
was our winter.
So, I think that just kind of adds to it. So, can we have something in place or maybe have the, if we don't have the land use attorney maybe present at the next meeting?
>> We will try. I can't guarantee that we will have, somebody
here. I'm you know, if
I would like to get the the property owner and the engineer both here. We have been unsuccessful in doing that and
not making that a big enough issue.
And if I get them here, I would like to have attorney grants here as well. So we're we're shooting to try to do that for the next meeting to
wrap that up.
>> Yes. That's what I was getting at. Okay. Good. Thanks.
Okay.
>> Hope a lot changes for the better between now and then.
>> Yes.
And and I will try so
and I will try to have the next meeting
to be the hybrid variety because I know Mark Branch doesn't like going
out after dark and he just assumed log in from home and that sort of thing too. So
we'll
try to make that for the next meeting here.
>> Okay, I think that would help us make some progress that has really stalled.
Then yes, thank you. And then to move on, yes, I can see what you posted about the accessory apartments.
>> Okay, I'm going to go through this quickly. There's only one thing that I changed since we talked about this before.
But again, back, you know, in the in the intent thing there, if you provide for the needs of the elderly, we cross that out because,
while that was the intention when we first put these regs in here, you know, it it's now the intention to this be an affordable housing
solution for people that are just starting out. So we just got rid of those words.
Moving down to, paragraph four eleven dash point two.
The intent here
was to
make everything by site plan review. So I had to refer the dash principal dwelling
in there because that follows the guidance from the state. Know,
we saw from all the public.
Interest in the accessory department for tonight, I think that's going to be the case with most of them, and we should just try to make that easier and go do site plan review.
The next one, looking down just a little bit there, we we talked about
yeah. Here it go.
You're gonna have to scroll down. Is it probably down there? My finger works out of mouse, not on the pad very well. Okay. Thank you. That'll be good. So,
We had an accessory apartment that didn't
meet the size of the lock requirement
of our, you know, section 11.2,
and we did not allow that.
Based on, you know, the knowledge now that we
we cannot make a minimum size on a
house
and also that
The state wanted us to have.
Having a matter of right that anybody could put an accessory apartment on any lot.
I got rid of what I did is I set the setback requirements of section 11.2
are satisfied,
and so you know we should still meet the setback requirements,
but if the lot is smaller than 60,000 square feet got rid of that requirement.
Moving down to the beat we talked about the net floor area no
larger than 1,000 square feet consistent with the state
and no larger than 33% of the groups
or the net floor area of the single family dwelling.
Net floor area is defined in section 24.
And that all lines us up with what the state would say in there.
They have no minimum. They have no minimum. Correct.
>> There's technically
a minimum imposed by the state building code.
Because there is a minimal habitable area
for sleeping area.
So there's not
no minimum, but it's pretty small.
It's, you know, in order of 120
square feet, something like that.
So just to let you know, okay,
>> the change that I made that you hadn't seen before is in item
D here.
And I put, you know, the the principal dwelling in Century Park and show remain under common ownership. And I added the words in the owner shall reside in either the principal dwelling or the accessory apartment.
And when we first put
these regulations into effect,
you know, we were talking about having
the the person in the accessory apartment had to be a family member. And we said, well, what happens when that person dies? You know, we spent all this money making this thing. When we get in, so we made it so that
it could it could be rented out for, you know, affordable housing and that kind of thing.
And in that we lost maybe the the thought that we liked
having
the
owner
reside on the property, if we're putting you know two two dwellings now on a single lot, having the owner live there
probably
adds a level of oversight
before it gets to the town's business,
maybe keeping things under control.
And so I put those words in there. That's a little different.
Jim thinks we had talked about that one time before. I couldn't remember if we had or not, but I was interested in any feedback if you think we're going too much. That is not in the example that the state gave us
for doing. They don't say anything about that, but I do think that it's
nice to have, you
know, you're not having one person owning two rental properties on a on a single lot. It it helps keep
the
good neighbors
good.
Any anybody got any thoughts
on that one way or the other?
I agree with it. I mean, if you have two rental properties on the same property,
you're essentially an apartment complex at that point, right? Yeah. And and the town is going to be the receiver of all the
Complaints, you know, it would be nice to have the property owner
put his degree of, you know, he's trying to maintain some
semblance of decorum and doing that. So Okay.
I leave that in there. That doesn't mean it's a done deal. You know, we're at some point.
You know, after tonight, I plan to send these over to Mark Ranch, let him take a cut on it, and then we'll we'll see what is coming up next. He's pulled that over here. Yeah.
>> We'll get that reviewed by him. Good. Good. Good. I got that.
I just question whether that's the default.
Not that I disagree with.
>> Okay,
that's good. So again, we
had some discussion last meeting about,
you know, what what should the architectural plans require? You know, should we we talk about the electric? Should we talk about insulate and all those kind of stuff? And I and I thought about that a lot. I said that's really building officials
thing. It's gotta be made to code, you know, and so.
We'll we'll check with the building official on that to see where where he comes down on that, but I
can't imagine it not having to be built to code if somebody's gonna be living in it.
But,
and I took the words from the, the detached well and put it up here.
It says the architectural plan shall be submitted as part of the site plan review,
this is from our existing regs, to determine that the proposed structure is consistent and apparent from the character of the surrounding buildings.
It does not detract from the rural characteristics of the area.
So that's really all we're trying, In my mind, that's what we're trying to do from the architectural volumes is make sure that, you know, it's not some
funky looking building that doesn't tie in and
the rest of the neighborhood, that sort of thing.
>> Can I make one point though? Yep.
This is under site plan view.
So you can ask for architectural
plans
again, but unless you have some kind of design standard,
you can't reject them because you don't like their architectural plans.
He put if it was a special permit.
But how do you reject a site plan
if it needs code?
Or if it needs?
>> What one would look at would be architectural elevations to determine compliance
if it if it's performance with the neighborhood,
and it blends with the neighbors.
But there are some section there are a few
requirements in regulations
that would
that do require
a floor plan.
We
yeah. I understand. Yeah.
Certainly. We've got a kitchen and a bathroom. Right. And a living space.
>> Yes. So in that,
that's listed in there. It's in one of those
things and thoughts about that.
They just got a living
area,
sanitary and kitchen.
>> But I guess my point is that
if you're talking about if you're set a detached structure now is only site plan review,
yet you think you're going to review their architectural
and reject something just because you don't like their architectural.
Yeah, you don't have a good leg to stand on. Okay.
>> No, that's true. For a site plan review.
I'll consider that.
Yeah. I
good point. Thank you.
Because we've got it down there.
It's such a good point that we made it twice. It's in f and I as well, not consistent with the character. It's all through our our,
zooming rates. Right. Yeah. So
we can try.
Anyhow, there you go. And it got I think that gets to the end there.
But I did wanna put
a definition in our definition section about what architectural
drawings
would be. You scroll down here to the bottom of the the three definitions.
It says, yeah,
>> a little more because it says proposed architectural
plan definition for our regs.
We'll keep scrolling now. Yep. We got a little bit there. That's good. That's good.
Architectural
plans in architectural
building engineering and floor plan is a technical drawing with scale showing a view from above the relationship between rooms,
spaces,
traffic patterns, and other physical features
at one level of the structure. Conventions are usually drawn between the walls to specify room sizes and all lengths.
Floor plans may also include details of the features like sinks, water meters, furnaces,
etc. Floor plans may include
notes for construction specified finishes,
construction methods,
or symbols or electrical items.
So that's, you know, taking a look at a couple. I I know
I put a couple of the things I thought we were looking for, and so that would be my recommendation for what we would define in our architectural plan to put that into our section on deputy meetings. I think that definitely is fine for the floor plan that Jim mentioned elevations.
We're gonna
review the aesthetics.
So anyhow, that's it. That's all I wanted to go through tonight on the accessory apartment regulation. Anybody have any other comments on on
those, Leanne? I see it crossed off four point eleven point three, that whole section. What was the reason for that? Because we're not doing special permits in the That is correct. Yeah. The the goal was to eliminate any requirement to have a special permit for effective dwelling.
And so outside of the lake area, it's a it's a
matter of right for for anybody to to have a good one.
What about for any patient?
Bargain spaces, the it's still in there. You got you got two for the main home and one for the
accessory apartment.
Yeah. What is the principal plumbing? Like, 3,000 square feet, maybe 1,000
square foot house and three bedrooms.
One space still good enough?
It is. Yeah. They might wanna put two, but it's gotta have at least one. That's that's for That
is. Yeah. Matter of fact,
they reduced the number of burner spaces when they put out their guidance
two years ago.
There used to be two for the accessory department. They ordered it to one. Yes.
You're talking oh, okay. In fact, that was they just said you can't ask for more than that.
And they say you put it in, but we can't we can't specify between the target that notice.
It's more than three.
>> You guys had a debate about whether you require permanent foundations
for this structure?
>> We have not had that debate in in one of the things that, you know,
I
Well,
it I
just want to check that.
I gotta get a hold of the building guy to see does a house need to be
on a foundation
and
You
know, so we we said this is more like a house than a shed and and I'm sure Potter Farms is going to be big time as well as a bunch of other people into making sheds that get turned into accessory work. And
so
my
my thought was is you get ready for the the meeting tonight.
So when somebody comes and and they have a shed
put on the the the gravel rock biome,
is that okay? And I didn't know the answer to that yet.
And I don't I don't like it. You know, I think we need to require a foundation,
but I gotta find out if that's something the building official was or we need to put it in.
Yeah. Yeah. This is a chicken flag that Verizon is approved there. It is on its own. Yeah. No.
Excuse me? Is there anything else in the garage? We forgot about it. Oh, yeah. Yeah. Talk about it. That's why I don't agree with it.
You can turn the garage into a house.
There's no frost protection.
>> It's fairly common to have a garage area made into a part of the house, so I've seen that on many.
So
>> Yep. And I'm not smart enough to say, yeah, I don't know what the fraud protections. The differences are.
My conclusion was that we need a foundation, whatever that is, and I don't know how you define a foundation.
I've lived in lots of places where they had houses on slash. It just wasn't here in New England,
so I don't know.
Some of these tiny homes are built on trailers?
Well, in in that's
yes.
So that's the technical detail
I need to come through with
the
accessory department on the on the rock band.
We're on wheels. We're on wheels.
Right? They can be. Yeah.
>> This guy's a boat on it for you.
$30.
Yep.
Yeah, I know there.
It's
a complex issue. And obviously, every state deals with it
differently.
I mean, there are a lot of pre manufactured
what they call granny pods or menu pods
that you can buy and put on fully assembled.
>> You know, the question becomes how is that different than somebody wants to park in your street trailer? And you're somebody live there? They wanted their usage of the one of their usage on that?
Don't know. I
got more homework to do on that. That would just, you know, because I was thinking about the, you know, the nice shed get pulled in and upgraded in the comment there.
And I got smart enough on the foundation requirements here. My
thought was building official should require a foundation.
If not, we'll go ahead.
>> Well, but do you consider I mean, there's a lot of possibilities.
I mean, one, you could just do a slab and they do thickened. So they take down both feet on the edge and they pour on,
you know, a model
for 12 hunched wall, right?
Bunch of different names for but basically essentially get to your
your frost wall built into the slab. Yeah, you can also do a
slab that sits on top of a sufficiently
thick stack of foam
and
do an insulated slab
without going down four feet. There's a lot of
and I don't know how the Connecticut building codes,
like a lot of northern areas,
you know, it's more common to use the insulated
air slap on grade foundations.
You have to see what what was allowed, but I would be
you know, the good thing about it is the smaller the house gets,
the less critical because,
you know, if you have a really big building settling in one side versus the other shows up and causes you a lot of problems.
If you have a 12 by 20 structure,
little settling on one side, we don't do that big a deal.
Can be double.
That's my thoughts.
Okay.
>> Anyhow, that's where we are on that. I want to go through those because we dealt with the excessive use today.
Next item up is the approval of the minutes from 03/20/2024.
And I'll make a motion to approve the meeting minutes from
03/20/2020.
Second.
The applicant's name is Byron and
five eighty.
Okay.
>> There's a couple of misspellings that I've given
to Maria.
But it requires just
for reference.
>> Any other comments, from anybody there?
The only other comment, that I had was on page three
just before we got to correspondence.
That has
four zero one Steve Nelson obtained.
We need to say the motion passed.
Any comments?
Okay.
Hearing none,
a call to approve the minutes as amended.
Ian?
Aye.
Scott? Aye. Steve? Aye. Leanne?
>> I vote aye as well. Vote in passing right zero.
Correspondence here.
None.
Okay. That's good.
Zoning
agents enforcement action pending applications.
>> 664 Route 6
Barnett Property,
long standing
flight violation,
joke violation,
and
the habitation of a habitation
of an RV.
I've been working spent a lot of time with
well, with
town attorney on this.
And, hopefully, we're well,
hopefully, we'll be filing leads
liens against the property
to reflect.
Fires have been levied
for both well,
for the for the blight as well as
as pending
zoning violation. I'm working with Mark Grant on the zoning violation that has yet to be
pursued.
Zoning violation specifically on the,
for junk on the property.
In
addition to, like,
a
long time, very time consuming project.
See some some progress
from an enforcement standpoint.
Progress meaning
actual orders issued and such fines being levied.
There's been some progress in charge,
junk removal, but it's eliminated.
And the the
was the health department did shut down the house,
which being
the house is no
longer
being occupied.
It has to be resolved. Their issues have to resolve before
it is occupied.
Motorhome,
as far as I know, is still being used. I'm working on that again with
Mark Brantz.
243 long held will let property
have back
from the road, the roof that they bought from it, get on the market. I have not pursued it because I
didn't know too much about it. I it has not sold.
I'm
going to issue
an order to an outstayed owner on that,
And, hopefully, we'll it's
there's a working on that.
Mills Property next to the library,
which is the fence that's been in disarray for the price of time.
I have been in contact with the owner. He has assured me he's purchased material.
And we'll be working on this hopefully,
any day now. Maybe he can take care of it in April.
I
have heard from fairly recently.
He's
on the case.
27 Hendy Road. This is a lot of blight.
It's a house under construction. Been under construction for a long time.
I have
mentioned it to the owner, not issuing an order, waiting for him to be looking for a CO.
I more recently, I have contacted him,
tried to put some issues out to him. But right now, I have
Permissions
from the CLVS to address.
There's some flight conditions there.
43 times far.
I have a an RV that's being resided in, has been for a long time.
The owner has assured me that as soon as campgrounds open,
the RV will be moved off-site.
I have not gone back to take a look at that in the last few weeks.
That's all I have. I'm happy to answer any questions.
>> That the new house I'm handing, did they put pins in there, Jim?
>> Pins?
When you do the CL, you're gonna inspect. I will. Yeah. I did not that I did not issue. I did not don't it's not not here when that started starting back in 2019 or in 2018,
2018.
I don't
I don't know the status of that as far as I mean, that wasn't a subdivision.
She had last been there for a long time.
But, nonetheless, yeah, I will I verify that.
>> They cleaned up the property on Long Hill, Jack The Cross. Oh, I have I forgot that one. I
>> actually haven't seen it. I saw the dumpster on-site. Yeah. Which depends on what you just like the scene of the days. A
lot better than it was. They might have
They told the whole dumpster.
>> It
was a project that was undertaken by by a partnership and which has since
been dissolved or or at least killed.
There's so there's one owner that I think will be focusing on that. And hopefully, he'll he will be on-site. You know, he will have a presence there.
Hopefully,
it's not gonna same thing is gonna happen. I didn't know that you had
I think it became a little more of a problem than the the state of the country.
And slow down and walk
up and and,
hopefully, they'll be back.
>> Any other questions for Jim?
Inland Wetlands Watercourse Commission liaison we had no meeting this month so nothing to report.
If somebody on the planning and zoning commission wants to be the liaison within the province,
I would be happy to entertain
shifting to their responsibility here. You need to be a voting member all the time in the wetlands application.
And it can be an alternate. And it can be an alternate. That's how I
started out over there as an alternate. And
so if you're interested, let me know.
Item 10 public comment. Any any public comments at this point?
>> Just do we? The next time
Not yet. Don't know. Small house. Small
house is obviously lifted.
I've seen the car here.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I was assured it wasn't done. I I don't doubt that
it is. I I was also told that the the owner
purchased a piece of commercial property and moved a lot of this equipment outside.
We're hopeful that but I'll I'll follow-up on that on that.
>> Yep. There's there's, like, one or two sheds. They're like a king or
something like a like, a building, but it's just very, very small.
It's a new
three
home occupation application for Merrick Valley Road. I
>> have been in contact with the gentleman who
hasn't been in.
Okay. So I'll chase her down. Yeah.
>> We owe it to
his neighbor to get
that adjudicated.
Okay.
Any other comments from public?
Okay. I've been here with you. Next
>> meeting,
the agenda says May 15. I was gonna be out of town then, so we moved it. It's on the it's on the schedule for May 22.
>> And
It is? It's on the regular meeting schedule? Yes. But it wasn't worth that, I think,
which is fine.
>> Now my, question,
for the commission here is looking ahead
to the July meeting, it'll probably start shifting to that third Tuesday,
like we had discussed,
because it's the start of the new year.
The, the June meeting is,
currently
scheduled Monday,
the twenty sixth.
I guess I'm inclined to leave it there. We can we can shift that to the third Tuesday and start that earlier
if anybody hear significantly
one way or the other.
But if not, we'll just stick with the schedule until July and then shift to,
the the third Tuesday.
Okay. Hearing none. Stay with the schedule as it currently is.
Miscellaneous.
Marina
is here tonight
doing her
minutes.
Carol Ann, since the last meeting, resigned.
And so
Marina is gonna be helping us out with
the minutes
Any
>> other missile media topics that we should talk about?
Leanne, how did it work from your end up there?
>> Quite well. Thank you for, sharing the screen a couple times when I apparently wouldn't otherwise have been able to see it.
>> Were you able to hear everybody? I know a couple of the people sitting in the back of the room weren't always talking as loud as I would hope.
Did you make it out okay?
>> Yes,
sometimes that
room, even when for those of you there in person,
the acoustics have never been good, and it's been known for that for years,
but I feel like I was able to do quite well over the phone.
>> Okay. Thank you, Leanne. Any
other miscellaneous time?
Last item is adjourned. We make the motion we adjourn. I'll
second.
Got a second. Any opposed?
It's unanimous. Five zero zero. Thank you all for
the